# Xiufeng Liu Senior Researcher

- Email: xiuli@dtu.dk Phone: +45-9351 1339
- Address: R125, Building 426, DTU, 2800 Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark
- Homepage: http://xiufengliu.github.io Google Scholar: https://goo.gl/7qMrt2
- Open-source software at Github: https://github.com/xiufengliu

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

The primary goal of my research is to develop fundamental concepts and new solutions for big data analysis and management related to smart energy. My current work has concentrated on three key areas: Building scalable systems for big data analysis and management in the cloud; Using statistics, data mining and machine learning technologies to extract information from big data to support decision makings; Developing synergy solutions for smart cities in the disciplines, including energy economics and modelling, climate economics and science, information and communication technologies.

## **EDUCATION**

Aalborg University, Denmark PhD in Computer Science	08/2008 – 05/2012
<b>Tsinghua University, China</b> MSc in Software Engineering	09/2002 – 06/2015
<b>Tsinghua University, China</b> BSc in Computer Science	09/1997 – 06/2001

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Technical University of Denmark Senior Researcher, Department of Management Engineering	10/2018 – Present
Technical University of Denmark Researcher, Department of Management Engineering	01/2017 – 09/2018
Technical University of Denmark Postdoc, Department of Management Engineering	01/2015 – 12/2016
University of Waterloo, Canada Postdoc, Department of Management Engineering	01/2013 – 12/2014
Aalborg University, Denmark Research Assistant, Department of Computer Science	06/2012 – 12/2012
Abo Akademic University, Finland Research Assistant, Department of Computer Science	09/2006 – 07/2008

#### **GRANTS**

- CVAES: Cognitive Visual Analytics for Smart Energy Systems, EuroTech Postdoc Project, Date: 1/9 2019 31/8 2021
- FlexSUS: Flexibility for Smart Urban Energy Systems, Role: Participant, Date: 1/9 2019 31/8 2022
- EMB3Rs: User-driven Energy- Matching & Business Prospection Tool for Industrial Excess Heat / Cold Reduction, Recovery and Redistribution. EU H2020 Project, Date: 1/9 2019 31/8 2023
- HEAT 4.0: Digitally supported Smart District Heating (Nr. 8090-00046A), Role: WP2 lead, Date: 19/3 2019 18/3 2022
- FED: Flexible Energy Denmark, Role: Participant, Date: 9/4 2019 8/4 2023
- Roskilde Smart Monitoring Household project, Role: Principal Investigator, Date: 01/01/2018 05/31/2019
- 2-year IBM Research Fellowship, 2013
- Best paper, The 18th International Conference on Extending Database Technology, 2015.
- 3-year PhD Research Fellowship, 2008

#### SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

#### **PhD Thesis**

- Data intelligence for district heating management, 2019 2022
- Benchmarking Residential Energy Consumption In Indonesia, Co-supervised with Prof. Per Severts Nielsen, 2016 2019.
- Statistical analysis of high impact climate projections and their economic consequences, Cosupervised with Prof. Kirsten Halsnæs, 2016 2019

#### **Postdoc Project**

• CVAES: Cognitive Visual Analytics for Smart Energy Systems, 1/10 2019 – 30/9 2011

## **Master Thesis**

- Ontology-based Big Dimension Design for Data Warehouse, 2011
- Data Warehousing and Data Warehouse Design, 2010

## PUBLICATIONS H-index (GoogleScholar): 14, Citations (GoogleScholar): 567+

## Refereed Journal Papers (\* - Corresponding author)

- 1. **X. Liu**, Y. Yang, L. Li, and P.S. Nielsen. A Stochastic Model for Residential User Activity Simulation, Accepted by Energies, 2019.
- 2. S. Khan, M. Alam, X. Liu, and K.A. Shakil. Big Data Technology-Enabled Analytical Solution for Quality Assessment of Higher Education Systems. International Journal of Advanced Computer Science and Applications, 10(6):292-304, 2019.
- 3. **X. Liu**, N. Iftikhar, H. Huo, R. Li, and P.S. Nielsen. Two Approaches for Synthesising Scalable Residential Energy Consumption Data, Journal of Future Computer Systems, vol. 95, pp. 586–600, 2019.
- 4. **X. Liu**, and P. S. Nielsen. Scalable Prediction-based Anomaly Detection on Smart Meter Data. Journal of Information Systems, Vol. 77, pp. 34-47, 2018.
- 5. P. Gianniou, **X. Liu**\*, A. Heller, P. S. Nielsen, and C. Rode. Clustering-based Analysis for Residential District Heating Data. Journal of Energy Conversion & Management, vol 165, pp. 840–850, 2018.
- 6. **X. Liu**, P. S. Nielsen, and A. Heller. CITIESData: a smart city data management framework. Journal of Knowledge and Information Systems (KAIS), 53(3): 699–722, 2017.
- 7. S. Khan, **X. Liu**, K. A. Shkil, and M. Alam. A Survey of Scholarly Data: From Big Data Perspective. Journal of Information Processing and Management (IPM), 53(4):923-944, 2017.
- 8. A. Heller, **X. Liu**, and P. Gianniou. A Science Cloud for Smart Cities Research. Energy Procedia 122: 679–684, 2017.
- 9. **X. Liu**, L. Golab, W. Golab, I. F. Ilyas, and S. Jin. Smart Meter Data Analytics: Systems, Algorithms and Benchmarking. ACM Transaction of Database System (TODS), 42(1), 2016.
- 10. **X. Liu**, P. S. Nielsen. An ICT-Solution for Smart Meter Data Analytics. Journal of Energy, 115(3):1710–1722, 2016.
- 11. **X. Liu**, N. Iftikhar, and P. S. Nielsen. Optimizing ETL by a Two-level Data Staging Method. International Journal of Data Warehousing and Mining (IJDWM), 12(3):32–50, 2016.
- 12. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen, ETLMR: A Highly Scalable Dimensional ETL Framework Based on MapReduce. TLDKS III, LNCS 7790, 8:1–31, 2013.
- 13. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. MapReduce-based Dimensional ETL Made Easy (demo). PVLDB 5(12):1882–1885, 2012.
- 14. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. 3XL: Supporting efficient operations on very large OWL Lite triple-stores. Journal of Information Systems, 36(4):765–781, 2011.
- 15. **X. Liu**. A Data Warehouse Solution for E-Government. International Journal of Research and Reviews in Applied Sciences, 4(1):120-128, 2010.
- 16. S. Kang and X. Liu. Online Model-based Testing Design Using the Qtronic Tool. Journal of Northeast Normal University (Natural Science Edition), 42(4):1–8, 2010.

## **Refereed Conference Papers**

- 1. **X. Liu**, S. Bolwig, and P.S. Nielsen. SmartM: A Non-intrusive Load Monitoring Platform, Workshop of the 22nd Business Information System, pp. 1–10, 2019.
- 2. A. Kewo, P. Manembu, **X. Liu**, P.S. Nielsen. Statistical Analysis for Factors Influencing Electricity Consumption at Regional Level. Proc. of IEEE 7th International Conference on Power and Energy (PECon), pp. 132-137, 2018.

- 3. **X. Liu**, R. Li, and P. S. Nielsen. User Activity Simulation for Residential Buildings. Accepted by the 13th Conference on Sustainable Development of Energy, Water and Environment Systems (SDEWES), 2018.
- 4. L. Liu, H. Huo, X. Liu, V. Palade. Recognizing Textual Entailment with Attentive Reading and Writing Operations. Proc. of the 23rd International Conference of Database Systems for Advanced Applications (DASFAA), pp. 847–860, 2018.
- 5. D. Ahlers, F. Kraemer, A. E. Braten, X. Liu, F. Anthonisen, P. Driscoll and J. Krogstie. Analysis and Visualization of Urban Emission Measurements in Smart Cities (demo). Proc. of the 21st International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT), pp. 698–701, 2018.
- 6. A. Kewo, P. Manembu, P. S. Nielsen, and **X. Liu**. Modelling of electricity consumption in one of the Asia's most populous cities Jakarta, Indonesia. Proc. of the 12th Conference on Sustainable Development of Energy, Water and Environment Systems (SDEWES), 2017.
- 7. H. Huo, **X. Liu**, D. Zheng, Z. Wu, S. Yu, L. Liu. Collaborative Filtering Fusing Label Features Based on SDAE. Proc. of ICDM, pp. 223–236, 2017.
- 8. **X. Liu**, P. S. Nielsen, A. Heller, and P. Gianniou. SciCloud: A Scientific Cloud and Management Platform for Smart City Data. Proc. of DEXA Workshop, pp. 27–31, 2017.
- 9. **X. Liu**, P. S. Nielsen, and A. Heller. An ICT-based Anomaly Detection Method for Smart Meter Data. Proc. of the 12th Conference on Sustainable Development of Energy, Water and Environment Systems (SDEWES), 2017.
- 10. N. Iftikhar, X. Liu, F. E. Nordbjerg, S. Danalachi, and J. H. Vollesen. A Scalable Smart Meter Data Generator Using Spark. Proc. of the 25th International Conference on Cooperative Information Systems, 2017.
- 11. **X. Liu**, and P. S. Nielsen. Air Quality Monitoring System and Benchmarking. Proc. of the 19th International Conference on Big Data Analytics and Knowledge Discovery (DaWaK), pp. 459–470, 2017.
- 12. P. Manembu, B. Welang, A. Lapu, A. Kewo, P. S. Nielsen, and **X. Liu** A Novel Smart Meter Controlling System with Dynamic IP Addresses. Proc. of the 26th IEEE International Symposium on Industrial Electronics (ISIE 2017).
- 13. **X. Liu**, N. Iftikhar, P. S. Nielsen, and A. Heller. Online Anomaly Energy Consumption Detection Using Lambda Architecture. Proc. of the 18th International Conference on Big Data Analytics and Knowledge Discovery (DaWaK), pp. 193–209, 2016.
- 14. N. Iftikhar, X. Liu, F. E. Nordbjerg, and S. Danalachi. A Prediction-based Smart Meter Data Generator. Proc. of the 19th International Conference of Network-based Information Systems (NBIS), 2016.
- 15. H. Huo, **X. Liu**, J. Li, and H. Yang. A Weighted K-AP Query Method for RSSI based Indoor Positioning. Proc. of the 27th Australasian Database Conference (ADC), pp. 150–163, 2016.
- 16. **X. Liu**, Per Sieverts Nielsen. Streamlining Smart Meter Data Analytics. Proc. of the 10th Conference on Sustainable Development of Energy, Water and Environment Systems, SDEWES2015.0558,1–14, 2015.
- 17. N. Iftikhar, **X. Liu**, and F. E. Nordbjerg. Relational-Based Sensor Data Cleansing. Proc. of 19th East-European Conference on Advances in Databases and Information Systems (ADBIS), pp. 108–118, 2015.
- 18. **X. Liu**, N. Iftikhar. An ETL Optimization Framework Using Partitioning and Parallelization. Proc. of the 30th ACM/SIGAPP Symposium On Applied Computing (SAC), pp. 1015–1022, 2015.
- 19. **X. Liu**, L. Golab, I. F. Ilyas. SMAS: A Smart Meter Data Analysis System (demo). Proc. of the 31st International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE), pp. 1476–1479, 2015.
- 20. **X. Liu**, L. Golab, W. Golab, Ihab F. Ilyas. Benchmarking Smart Meter Data Analytics. Proc. of the 18th International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT), pp. 385–396, 2015 (Best Paper).
- 21. **X. Liu**, N. Iftikhar, and X. Xie, Survey of Real-time Processing Systems for Big Data. Proc. of the 18th International Database Engineering & Applications Symposium (IDEAS), pp. 356–361, 2014.
- 22. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen, CloudETL: Scalable Dimensional ETL for Hive. Proc. of the 18th International Database Engineering & Applications Symposium (IDEAS), pp. 195–206, 2014.
- 23. **X. Liu** and N. Iftkhar. Ontology-based Big Dimension modeling in Data Warehouse Schema Design, Proc. of the 12th Business Information System (BIS), pp. 75–87, 2013.

- 24. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. 3XL: An Efficient DBMS-Based Triple-Store. Proc. of DEXA Workshops, pp. 284-288, 2012.
- 25. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. ETLMR: A Highly Scalable Dimensional ETL Framework Based on MapReduce. Proc. of the 13th International Conference on Big Data Analytics and Knowledge Discovery (DaWaK), pp. 96–111, 2011.
- 26. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. The ETLMR MapReduce-Based ETL Framework. Proc. of the 23rd Scientific and Statistical Database Management Conference (SSDBM), pp. 586–588, 2011.

#### **Book Chapters**

1. **X. Liu**, H. Huo, N. Iftikhar, and P. S. Nielsen. A Two-Tiered Segmentation Approach for Transaction Data Warehousing. In Emerging Perspectives in Big Data Warehousing, pp. 1-27, IGI Global, 2019.

## **Technical Reports**

- 1. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. ETLMR: A Highly Scalable Dimensional ETL Framework Based on MapReduce, TR-29, Department of Computer Science, Aalborg University, 2011.
- 2. **X. Liu**, C. Thomsen, and T. B. Pedersen. CloudETL: Scalable Dimensional ETL for Hadoop and Hive, TR-30, Department of Computer Science, Aalborg University, 2012.
- 3. **X. Liu**, D. Truscan, and L. Lilius. Online Testing of the ABOT Game Server Using the Qtronic Tool, Turku Centre for Computer Science, 2008.